<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Agapai aspiloi, or The innocent love-feast. Being a sermon preached at S. Lawrence Jury in London, the sixth day of September, Anno Domini 1655. On the publick festival of the county of Hertford; and published this present May 1656. / By William Clarke.</title>
            <author>Clarke, William, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206588</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097635</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171239</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171239)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2569:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Agapai aspiloi, or The innocent love-feast. Being a sermon preached at S. Lawrence Jury in London, the sixth day of September, Anno Domini 1655. On the publick festival of the county of Hertford; and published this present May 1656. / By William Clarke.</title>
                  <author>Clarke, William, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Lee at the Turks Head in Fleet Street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Agapai aspiloi" appears in Greek letters on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped with some loss of print; the opening of p. [2-3] not filmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 1st IV, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR <hi>The Innocent Love-Feaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a SERMON Preached at S. LAWRENCE JURY in <hi>London,</hi> the ſixth day of September, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1655. On the publick Feſtival of the County of HERTFORD; And publiſhed this preſent May 1656.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM CLARKE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 9.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl> For <hi>Samuel</hi> came to day to the City, for there is a Feaſt of the People to day in the High-place:</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>—The People will not eat until he come, becauſe he doth bleſſe the Sacrifice, and afterwards they eat that be bidden.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>William Lee</hi> at the Turks Head in <hi>Fleet Street.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatory.</head>
            <p>Providence hath ſo ordered, that my <hi>Firſt-born</hi> ſhould be within my <hi>own Tribe:</hi> which, notwithſtanding is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge I truly value, yet I muſt confeſſe, the means of obtaining it, are ſo contrary to my private ſpirit, that had it not been for thoſe <hi>importunities</hi> which frequently aſſaulted an <hi>eaſie nature,</hi> I ſhould rather have choſen to have died <hi>childleſſe,</hi> then to have endured the <hi>hazards</hi> and <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences</hi> that attend <hi>poſterity</hi> in an <hi>Evil Age:</hi> But having neither <hi>obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> nor <hi>ill manners</hi> enough, to deny the ſolicitations of my Countrey-men, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of them that were the <hi>Prime Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of that dayes <hi>Ceremony;</hi> I have at laſt ſuffered my ſelf to be <hi>over-ruled</hi> againſt my own <hi>inclinations:</hi> And now, like a <hi>modeſt Woman</hi> in her <hi>firſt</hi> teem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I am ready to <hi>Bluſh</hi> at my Burden, and am <hi>affraid</hi> of the dangers of my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail,
<pb facs="tcp:171239:3"/> being as ſufficiently ſenſible of my <hi>own weakneſſe,</hi> as of the <hi>affronts</hi> and <hi>rudeneſſe</hi> of a <hi>Cenſorious Generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is a work yet more fearful to my thoughts, when I conſider, that by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing after <hi>this</hi> manner to the World, <hi>all</hi> thoſe <hi>blemiſhes</hi> which might haply be <hi>over-look'd</hi> in the Current of a <hi>ſwift</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery, must now be expoſed, as <hi>ſtanding objects,</hi> to the view of <hi>Learned, Serious,</hi> and, perhaps, ſevere <hi>Judges:</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which diſadvantage I may juſtly adde alſo, The <hi>weakneſſe</hi> which commonly accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies a <hi>Dead Letter,</hi> when it is parted from the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of a <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial diſpenſation;</hi> Eſpecially conſidering (for my own part) that if I have any <hi>perſonal endowment</hi> worth the <hi>own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> I may ſay without vanity, it lies rather in my <hi>Tongue</hi> then my <hi>Pen,</hi> my <hi>Hand</hi> (like <hi>Jacob</hi> in his diſguiſe) being much rougher then my voice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:4"/>
            <p>All which inconveniences <hi>(Dear Countreymen</hi>) I have named upon no other deſigne, but to let you ſee, that I value the <hi>Service of my Countrey,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my own <hi>Reputation;</hi> and that there is nothing too hard for me to <hi>grant,</hi> wherein you appear to be the <hi>ſuiters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if in review of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, you ſhall meet with any <hi>Doctrine, Precept,</hi> or <hi>Exhortation,</hi> that may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your <hi>Judgements,</hi> quicken your <hi>Obedience,</hi> or put a fervour into your <hi>Affections,</hi> let this <hi>Little Good</hi> expiate for all the <hi>imperfections</hi> of the <hi>Work,</hi> or <hi>infirmities</hi> of the <hi>Workman;</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this in minde, That it will be a very great <hi>diſorder</hi> to your <hi>deſigne,</hi> to be <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended</hi> at a <hi>Feaſt</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and to be <hi>cenſorious</hi> upon a Subject that pleads for <hi>Kindneſſe</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſſe.</hi> Let me therefore receive this as the <hi>Firſt-fruits</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171239:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of your Obedience to the Doctrine of <hi>Love,</hi> That you can receive with <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the <hi>plaineſt</hi> truths of Religion; and that you will think any Doctrine well worth the <hi>Printing,</hi> which is worth your <hi>Practiſing;</hi> which as it is the main <hi>End</hi> of all our <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſo let it be the <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py effect</hi> of this poor and unworthy <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> preſented you by the hands of him that is</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study at</hi> North Crawly <hi>in</hi> Bucks. <date>
                     <hi>Dec. 10. 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Dear Countrey-men Yours in the ſervice of Love W. CLARKE.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <list>
                  <head>Stewards</head>
                  <item>William Thomſon.</item>
                  <item>John Berresford.</item>
                  <item>John Ellis.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     </hi> Robert Waller</item>
                  <item>Robert Briſco.</item>
                  <item>Thomas Bateman</item>
                  <item>Richard Mead.</item>
                  <item>Joſeph Sible.</item>
                  <item>William Robinſon.</item>
               </list>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171239:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Innocent Love-Feaſt.</hi> OR, A Sermon preached at S. <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church in <hi>London</hi> the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>September, Anno Dom.</hi> 1655. On the publick Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival of the County of <hi>Hertford.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1</hi> Peter <hi>4. the former part of the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And above all things have fervent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity among your ſelves.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was no ſolemn Feaſt under the Law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Sacrifice annexed: to ſhew <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that, as Gods honour was the end, ſo Gods Grace and Benediction was the life of all their publick Feſtivals.<note place="margin">Chazkuni.</note> And whileſt (as the learned Rabbins obſerve) private or perſonal Oblations were offered in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; yet at the publick and ſolemn Feaſts of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> ever ſounded the ſilver Trumpets of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.<note place="margin">Num. 10.10: Pſal. 81.3.</note> Thus though the Charities and Hoſpitalities of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Families, are not accompanied with theſe publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations: yet how decent it is to ſound the Trumpets of Gods Sanctuary at the Feſtivall aſſembly of a whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, I need not ask you, who ſo laudably practiſe it? And
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171239:6"/> ſeeing I that am one of the meaneſt of the ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> am called to this religious Office, it will ill become me on this good day, to ſound in your ears the Alarmes of War; but rather, (as beſt anſwering the end and deſigne of this Chriſtian Convocation,) The Triumphs of Peace, and careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Chriſtian Charity. Which I cannot perform from a better hand nor in better words, then in this pregnant Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of the Apoſtle, now read unto you. <hi>And above all things have fervent charity among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Contexture</hi> of which words with the precedent and following verſes is not eaſie to be diſcerned; yet upon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent obſervation, we may finde this Chapter to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat <hi>Platform</hi> or Scheme of the whole courſe of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, through which he muſt run in this life; even from his new birth, to the goal of his death and diſſolution; for ſo it begins, and ſo it ends. The firſt ſteps he takes in this Race, are in the duties of Mortification, which is that <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in the fleſh,</hi> mentioned in the fifth verſe. Not meant of the <hi>Outward ſuffering</hi> in the Body by diſtreſſes or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions; for theſe ſufferings are towards the end of the Chapter, where he ſpeaks of the <hi>Fiery Trial, &amp;c.</hi> But the <hi>Suffering of the fleſh</hi> is here the <hi>inward ſuffering,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27.</note> and <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body into ſubjection</hi> (as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaks) by duties of mortification; the effect whereof is a <hi>negative holineſſe</hi> or <hi>ceaſing from ſin,</hi> which he enlargeth to verſe 7. <hi>It ſufficeth that we have ſpent the time paſt of our life in wantonneſſe, luſts, exceſſe of wine, revellings, banquetings, and abominable idolatries, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now although this ceaſing from ſin and <hi>negative holineſſe</hi> may carry us along the <hi>former part</hi> of our journey, through the duties of mortification; yet after this progreſſe made, we muſt haſten towards the <hi>End,</hi> by a motion of another nature,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.16.</note> to wit, not only of <hi>Mortification,</hi> but of <hi>Vivification;</hi> not onely <hi>ceaſing to do evil,</hi> but <hi>learning to do well,</hi> by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing ſpiritual graces in us, in all their variety and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency; unto all which the Apoſtle ſpeakes from ver. 7. to the end of the Chapter. Exhorting to the practiſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he ver. 7.) <hi>now the end is at hand,</hi> ye are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171239:6"/> not in the beginning of your journey, and therefore you muſt not reſt onely in <hi>Ceaſing from ſin;</hi> for the end is at hand, therefore you muſt <hi>do</hi> good and holy duties, of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> verſe 7. <hi>Be ſober and watch unto prayer;</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> ver. 8. <hi>Ahove all things have love or charity;</hi> of <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> verſe 9. <hi>Be harborours one to another;</hi> of miniſtring mutual <hi>Conſolation</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction</hi> verſe 10. <hi>As every man hath received the gift, ſo let him miniſter, as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God;</hi> and verſe 11. <hi>If any ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God—that God in all things may be glorified;</hi> of <hi>Conſtancy</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der perſecutions, from verſe 12. to the end of the Chapter, <hi>Think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery tryal;</hi> verſe 16. <hi>If any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian let him not be aſhamed;</hi> verſe 17. <hi>Judgement muſt begin at the houſe of God, &amp;c.</hi> And laſtly of the <hi>ultimate reſignation</hi> even of their ſoules in ſuffering for Gods cauſe, verſe the laſt, <hi>Let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit their ſoules to him in well doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you have ſeen how this Chapter containes an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act <hi>platform</hi> of a Chriſtians race; in which my Text points at one of thoſe <hi>good duties,</hi> which the Apoſtle requires, of them that are not onely to <hi>ceaſe from ſin,</hi> but to <hi>work righteouſneſs,</hi> and that not of the leaſt account neither; for after duties of <hi>ſobriety</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> it comes in with a <hi>But,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>But above all things have fervent charity among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which (if we may make <hi>Diviſions</hi> in a Text <hi>of Love,</hi>) may be divided into <hi>Four Parts:</hi> 1. Here is the <hi>Duty it ſelf</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, and that is Love or Charity, <hi>Have Charity.</hi> 2. Here is the <hi>Importance</hi> of that Duty, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Above all things have charity.</hi> 3. Here is the <hi>Qualification</hi> or <hi>Complexion</hi> of that Duty, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tranſlated, <hi>Fervent Charity.</hi> 4. Here is the <hi>Reciprocation</hi> of that Duty, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Among your ſelves. But above all things have fervent charity among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the <hi>Duty</hi> it ſelf enjoyned is Love or Charity, <hi>Have Charity:</hi> which is not in this place 1. That <hi>Cardinal</hi> Grace (as I may ſo call it) ſo highly extold by S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. which abideth in Heaven even after <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Propheſies,</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> ſhall fail, and which is preferr'd before <hi>Hope,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171239:7"/> and <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf; which in that place, is a comprehenſive name, including in it the perfection of all Graces and Duties both towards <hi>God,</hi> and towards our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it is ſaid <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.10. That <hi>Love is the fulfilling of the law.</hi> Neither Secondly, is this Love onely and meerly a <hi>Moral Love,</hi> ariſing from a complacency in a preſent good, found in Heathens and Unbelievers, and meer Natural Men, mentioned by our Saviour <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.46. <hi>If ye love them, that love you, what reward have you? do not even the Publicans the ſame?</hi> which is a <hi>Natural affection</hi> and not a <hi>Chriſtian grace,</hi> a <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane paſſion</hi> and not a <hi>Religious duty.</hi> Neither Thirdly is this Charity a bare <hi>Eleemoſynary Charity,</hi> of Almes and Good deeds, which in a ſtrict ſenſe is uſually called Charity, by attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting the <hi>inward affection</hi> of the minde to the <hi>outward action</hi> of the hand; mentioned 3 <hi>John</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>But this Charity in my Text is a <hi>Divine grace</hi> and a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duty, whereby we are to extend our bowels of love and Chriſtian compaſſion one towards another, not under the <hi>narrow relations</hi> of <hi>Kindred, Friends,</hi> or <hi>Benefactors,</hi> but unto <hi>all</hi> in the common capacity of Religion, and that not upon any humane or natural deſignes, which love is meerly a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral paſſion; but onely for <hi>Pious and Christian ends</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations; which turns Nature into Grace, and a Humane Paſſion into a Chriſtian Affection.</p>
            <p>Which being thus deſcribed unto us from the <hi>Original,</hi> the <hi>Object,</hi> and the <hi>End,</hi> by treating briefly of each of them apart, you will know ſufficient of the whole duty it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And Firſt for the <hi>Original</hi> of Chriſtian love; It is the grace of Gods holy Spirit: Indeed <hi>Love</hi> 1. As it is <hi>a paſſion of the Soul,</hi> ariſeth meerly from <hi>Nature;</hi> which is an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on placed originally in Man by the great Creator, whereby he takes complacency and content in the good things of the Creature which God hath made for him, without which all the bleſſings of this life were but in vain created, and were no more delicious to Man then to a Stock or Stone: That the pleaſant acceptation therefore of all Gods good things might not be loſt, did he indue Man with this natural affection of Love. But Love as it 2. is an <hi>inordinate paſſion</hi> ariſeth not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171239:7"/> from <hi>Nature Qua talis,</hi> but as corrupted and depraved <hi>by Sin,</hi> whereby the ſoul is <hi>Praeter inſtitutum naturae,</hi> carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the mediocrity of natural appetite towards the creature, and created bleſſings. While Man only loved the <hi>Creature,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>God;</hi> then he loved it in a mean and in a moderate ſubordination, to the love of God; who was to be loved with all our <hi>Might, Heart,</hi> and <hi>Strength.</hi> But when as by ſinne Mans heart forſook his God, then that earneſt and zealous love <hi>Ad ultimum poſſe</hi> before beſtowed upon the Almighty, was irregularly added to that mean and moderate Fountain of love of the Creature according to the Law of Nature; which great addition coming to the force of natural love, makes the ſoules of all corrupt unregenerate men run over their old banks towards the Creature, in a moſt inordinate meaſure and a moſt irregular manner, loving the Creature from two violent <hi>inforcements,</hi> one from <hi>Nature,</hi> the other from <hi>Luſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore to endeavour to reform this violent paſſion, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Precepts of Morality,</hi> or Rules of <hi>Depraved Reaſon,</hi> or the like Philoſophick aides, will prove as great a folly, as to ſet obſtacles in the midſt of a ſtrong torrent to prevent Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: they may perhaps give a check for a time, and make luſt ſuſpend a while the actual exerciſe of her inordinacy; but in the mean while ſhe gathers ſtrength, and will, as ſoon as ever thoſe violent reſtraints be remitted (which cannot be perpetual) overflow our ſoules with the greater flood of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and carry our hearts without poſſibility of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance down the ſtream from God towards the World. So that there is no means left to weaken <hi>this torrent,</hi> and to keep it within its due limits, but by dealing with the Fountain; the <hi>Heart</hi> muſt be changed and renewed, and the inclinations and deſires of our ſoules muſt be altered, which thing is neither in the power of <hi>Nature,</hi> nor <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but only <hi>of the grace of Gods Spirit</hi> to effect, which is able to re-inkindle that religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous love in our hearts, with which Man at firſt loved both God and his Brother: which was the ground of S. <hi>Johns</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, 1 Ep. 4.7, 8. <hi>Let us love one another, for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God; God is love,</hi> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 8.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171239:8"/> The original then of this religious love is Gods grace, which is the <hi>firſt part</hi> of the deſcription.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider the <hi>Object</hi> of this love, which is ſaid in the deſcription to be extended, not onely to <hi>Kindred, Friends,</hi> or <hi>Benefactors,</hi> but unto <hi>All</hi> in the capacity and latitude of Religion. The <hi>generick</hi> Object of all love is one and the ſame, and that is a <hi>preſent good</hi> either <hi>real</hi> or <hi>appearing:</hi> the vileſt wretch yet never loved evil <hi>Sub ratione mali,</hi> not as evil, but at leaſt under the appearance of good: But the <hi>Specifick</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are vaſtly different, nay, to ſhew the wonderful power of Grace over Nature, their Objects are contrariant, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite one to another, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.43, 44. <hi>In old time it was, thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour, and hate thy Enemy;</hi> this is the voice of Nature, and of the Old Man in the old time; But I ſay unto you, verſe 44. which is the voice of Grace and Chriſt, <hi>Love your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you, and do good to them that hate you.</hi> Hence is it that the Scripture makes no difference in Offices of love and mutual relief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Foe;</hi> but he that in one Precept is called our <hi>Enemy,</hi> in the recital of the <hi>ſame</hi> Precept in another place is called <hi>our Brother,</hi> and both to be loved and ſerved alike, as appears <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.4. compared with <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.1. In one place it is, <hi>If thine enemies Ox or his Aſſe go aſtray, thou ſhalt ſurely bring it back:</hi> in the other, which is the recital of the ſame Law, it is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee thy brothers Ox or his Aſſe go aſtray, but thou ſhalt in any caſe bring him back:</hi> So that, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be <hi>Enemy,</hi> or <hi>Brother,</hi> it is all one in the eye of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and both to be alike beloved, aſſiſted, and relieved.</p>
            <p>Which although it be very ſevere to Nature, yet the Chriſtian Law of love requireth it at our hands, never ſeeking to <hi>comply</hi> with, but to <hi>over-rule</hi> all our unregenerate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in ſo much that a new man at his firſt converſion is in nothing more an <hi>Ephraimite,</hi> like a young <hi>Heifer</hi> unaccuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſtrugling under the <hi>Yoke of Grace,</hi> then in reſpect to thoſe impulſions and checks which <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> impoſeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mans <hi>Affections:</hi> For indeed if you obſerve the Law of Grace and the Goſpel; this contrariety is not found only in this <hi>one</hi> affection of <hi>Love;</hi> but all the reſt of the paſſions, by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171239:8"/> the power and conſtraint of Grace, are not only <hi>diverted</hi> but <hi>inverted,</hi> &amp; turned cleer backward in their motions to objects diametrically oppoſite to their former. Thus for our <hi>Hatred, We muſt hate Father and Mother, and Wife, and Children, and Brethren, &amp; Siſters, and our own lives alſo, or we cannot be Chriſts Diſciples, Luke</hi> 14.26. Next for our <hi>Joy, We muſt joy in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, reproaches, calamities, and be exceeding glad, Mat.</hi> 5.13. Nay, <hi>Leap for joy</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is Chriſts word in S. <hi>Luke</hi> chap. 6.23.) <hi>when men hate you and reproach you;</hi> and ſo in all the reſt. Which although it may ſeem to be a very ſharp uſage of Nature, yet is it not without ſufficient reaſon and abundant compenſation; in regard that by vertue of the divine <hi>Chimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry</hi> of Grace, <hi>Good,</hi> even <hi>ſpiritual</hi> good is brought out of <hi>natural evils;</hi> according to <hi>S. Pauls</hi> word of conſolation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>We know that all things work together for good to them that love God.</hi> Even enemies, reproaches, and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Which is a Paradox to Nature, becauſe it is beyond her <hi>Ken</hi> or <hi>Comprehenſion:</hi> the <hi>Back</hi> cannot feel any good in <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>nakedneſſe,</hi> nor the <hi>Belly</hi> in <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>emptineſſe:</hi> and on the other ſide, they cannot apprehend there is any <hi>Evil</hi> in <hi>food</hi> and <hi>raiment;</hi> and as they <hi>judge,</hi> ſo they love and ſo they hate: But Grace comes and findes <hi>Wantonneſſe</hi> in <hi>fulneſſe of bread;</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> in <hi>gorgeous apparel:</hi> and on the other ſide, it findes <hi>Humility</hi> in <hi>rags; Chaſtity,</hi> in <hi>hunger</hi> and abſtinence; it findes <hi>Patience</hi> under <hi>afflictions;</hi> triumphs under perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and thus they work together for the good of them that love God. And thus much of the <hi>Object.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider the <hi>End</hi> of Chriſtian charity, which is ſaid in the Deſcription to be, <hi>Not upon any humane or natural deſigne, but for pious and Chriſtian ends and conſiderations.</hi> There are three <hi>Stages</hi> of all Mans actions, <hi>Himſelf,</hi> his <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and his <hi>God.</hi> Now 1. to love meerly for a mans <hi>own good, </hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and upon <hi>ſelf intereſt,</hi> is baſely <hi>Carnal,</hi> nay 'tis <hi>Ethnick; Do not even,</hi> the Heathen, <hi>the Publicans the ſame?</hi> Nay, 'tis Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, for the Beaſts love their Feeder for his food; but if he withholds his hand, and hunger begins to gripe thoſe Sava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <hi>Exaſperatur mitigata torvit as,</hi> they flye in his face that nouriſhed them, and make a prey of their Benefactor. And,
<pb facs="tcp:171239:9"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, to love our Brother meerly for our <hi>Brothers</hi> ſake, at beſt is but <hi>moral,</hi> in which reſpect though Man even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der depravation excels the bruit Beaſts, whoſe love (if I may ſo call it) reacheth no further then the firſt ſort, loving all things as they are agreeable or ſerviceable to their own ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive appetites: whereas this <hi>moral love</hi> in Man, admits not of ſuch mean mercenary reflections, and is beſtowed upon no other conſiderations then the goodneſſe, vertue, and merit of the perſon beloved, as a debt due to his worth &amp; goodneſs, which is the love of Philoſophers, and that which is called <hi>Amor Amicitiae</hi> or <hi>Benevolentiae;</hi> the love of Friendſhip and Good-will: yet is this love as far below the duty of the Text, and the affection of true Chriſtians, as it is above the luſt of Beaſts and brutiſh Men. Thirdly therefore, there is another <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſort of love which is neither for our <hi>own ſakes,</hi> nor <hi>our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> but for <hi>Gods ſake,</hi> and that not only in obedience to Gods <hi>Commandment</hi> of love, which is the Evangelick Law, and the <hi>New Command;</hi> nor for the conſervation of the peace of <hi>Gods Church,</hi> which is fortified by love; but alſo and principally, when it is beſtowed in conſideration of that <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual relation</hi> which our Brethren by grace have to God, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his praiſe, as <hi>Members,</hi> or as <hi>Miniſters</hi> of his Church; as parts of the <hi>houſhold of faith,</hi> &amp;c. This is to love our Brother for <hi>Gods</hi> ſake: Or in our Saviours phraſe, when we love a <hi>Diſciple</hi> in <hi>the name</hi> of a <hi>Diſciple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.41, 42</note> and a <hi>Prophet</hi> in the <hi>name</hi> of a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>righteous</hi> Man in the <hi>name</hi> of a <hi>righteous</hi> man. That is, when we love them under that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in which they ſtand towards God and Religion, which ought to be ſo predominant in every good heart, that it ſhould give <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> to all <hi>inferior relations</hi> whatſoever, whether <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Moral;</hi> in ſo much that if ever their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts ſtand in <hi>oppoſition,</hi> theſe ſubordinate indeerments ought to be utterly ſuperſeded and neglected, which is the reaſon our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, That <hi>unleſſe we hate father and mother, &amp;c. we cannot be his Diſciples.</hi> There are but <hi>three</hi> ſorts of inferior indeerments imaginable: Either the <hi>natural</hi> endearments of <hi>Blood; Moral</hi> of <hi>Friendſhip;</hi> or <hi>Politick</hi> endearments of neighbourhood, and commerce: and, as if the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:171239:9"/> had deſigned to ſhew at once, the ſupremacy of this <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> endearment of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> above them all, I finde all theſe <hi>Three</hi> expreſly ſuperſeded in <hi>one verſe</hi> for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Religion and Honour of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.27. When the people ſinned in the matter of the <hi>Golden Calf, Moſes</hi> from God required the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> to gird every Man his ſword to his ſide, and <hi>Slay every man his</hi> Brother, <hi>every man his</hi> Companion, <hi>and every man his</hi> Neighbour. Every Man his <hi>Brother,</hi> there's the <hi>natural</hi> endeerment of <hi>Blood;</hi> every Man his <hi>Companion,</hi> there's the moral endeerment of <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> and every Man his <hi>Neighbour,</hi> there's the <hi>pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tick</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deerment of <hi>Neighbourhood</hi> or <hi>Commerce,</hi> and all to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeded for the intereſt of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> Neither yet is our profeſſion (compoſed of ſuch ſevere Precepts) to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either <hi>Cruel</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural:</hi> Becauſe this <hi>Supreme</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> Relation doth not <hi>cancel</hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, but only <hi>ſuſpends</hi> their vertue and influence, like the <hi>Star</hi> in the preſence of the <hi>Sun,</hi> they <hi>are</hi> though they <hi>appear not;</hi> and ſo ſoon as ever this <hi>Ruling light</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and the Intereſt of <hi>Gods glory</hi> is not concerned to the contrary, then have theſe <hi>leſſer</hi> inducements their proper and allowable light and influence upon our affections: which is the reaſon why that <hi>Rigid</hi> paſſage in <hi>S. Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cha. 14. v. 26 Cha. 10. v. 37.</note> which ſeems to require an utter <hi>ſtifling</hi> of natural affection, in <hi>S. Matthew</hi> pleads only for a <hi>qualifying</hi> and <hi>ſubjecting</hi> it to <hi>Religion;</hi> and whileſt Chriſt ſaith in the one Evangeliſt; that <hi>Unleſſe we</hi> Hate <hi>Father and mother, &amp;c. we cannot be his Diſciples,</hi> he ſaith in the other Evangeliſt, <hi>He that loveth father and mother</hi> more <hi>then me is not worthy of me,</hi> pleading for no more but a due preference of <hi>Religion</hi> before <hi>Nature:</hi> Like holy <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> love to his ſon, which, whether it was the love of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> he knew not ſo well, as he did, when God put that ſevere command upon him, of offering his dear ſon; and by that ready ſubmiſſion his heart yielded to the will of God, he knew aſſuredly he loved his childe, not ſo much with the <hi>fondneſſe</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> as with the true <hi>affection of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and in ſubordination to God and his Honour. And if God, at any time, in mercy denies us theſe coſtly trials, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171239:10"/> will not ſhew us what is our love of our Children, Brethren, or Friends, by the loſſe of them, there is yet a leſſe <hi>charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> way to try the <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>our love,</hi> and that is by <hi>our anger.</hi> Doeſt thou conceive a <hi>Religious diſpleaſure</hi> againſt thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when thou ſeeſt him run into ſin, and diſhonour God, and break his Lawes, even then when all <hi>other conſiderations</hi> hold out as amiable as ever? then if thy <hi>Anger</hi> be religious, its a great ſigne ſuch is thy <hi>Love</hi> alſo. But on the contrary, Art thou not more angry with him, for denying thee a <hi>reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable courteſie</hi> at thy need, or for doing thee ſome <hi>conceived injury,</hi> or revealing ſome <hi>intruſted ſecret,</hi> or the like; then for being <hi>drunk,</hi> or <hi>profaning</hi> Gods Sabbath, or <hi>blaſpheming</hi> Gods Name, or for <hi>violating</hi> Gods Ordinances? if ſo, its an evident ſigne that this Love is but Carnal, and not that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly and divine affection which ownes no end or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above that ſupreme end and intereſt of <hi>God and Religion;</hi> which is the laſt Branch of the deſcription of this Duty, to wit, the <hi>End</hi> of our <hi>Charity,</hi> not for our <hi>own ſakes,</hi> nor for our <hi>Brothers,</hi> but for <hi>Gods ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that (to reunite that deſcription we have thus diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that we may ſee the full nature of this duty in one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect) we learn from what hath been ſpoken; Firſt, for the <hi>Original,</hi> That true Chriſtian Love is a ſtream derived not from the <hi>lower</hi> ſprings of <hi>Nature,</hi> nor <hi>loweſt</hi> of <hi>Luſt,</hi> but from the <hi>upper</hi> ſprings of Gods grace. Secondly, For its <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> That this ſtream muſt not only water the pleaſant Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and fruitful Valleys; but muſt alſo glide upon hard Rocks, and barren and unſavoury Bogs: For we muſt love our <hi>Enemies,</hi> and do good to them that <hi>hate us,</hi> and pray for them that <hi>deſpightfully uſe us.</hi> And Thirdly, for it its <hi>End:</hi> we learn firſt, That as this current of Divine Love of our Brother, muſt have no <hi>Back Stream,</hi> no <hi>Mercenary Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> upon our own intereſt, for this is baſely Carnal: And as, Secondly, it muſt not pour it ſelf ſolely and finally into our Brothers boſome for his <hi>own</hi> ſake; for this is a Ciſtern of our own hewing, and will hold no water when God accounts with us, it being at beſt but moral. So Thirdly we learn, That as Water <hi>In tantum aſcendit, in quantum prius deſcendit,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171239:10"/> it riſeth exactly as high in the Conduit as it fell from the Fountain; even ſo true Chriſtian love, as it is a ſtream deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Gods grace,</hi> ſo it muſt end in <hi>Gods glory</hi> and for <hi>Gods ſake:</hi> which is the full nature of Chriſtian Love, the <hi>Duty it ſelf</hi> enjoyned in this Text; <hi>Above all things have charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly it is not more lovely and heavenly in its <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> then conſiderable in its <hi>Importance,</hi> for ſo ſaith the Text, <hi>Above all things</hi> have charity: Whether we conſider it in its <hi>Precedence</hi> or <hi>Preheminence,</hi> both evidently intimated from the difference between the Latine and Engliſh in the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Original: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ante omnia</hi> ſaith the Latine, <hi>Before all things have charity,;</hi> There's the <hi>Precedent</hi> of the Duty: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Above all things</hi> ſaith the Engliſh, there's the <hi>Preheminence,</hi> both ſpeak the importance of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Before</hi> all things have charity. The love of our Brethren is a <hi>precedent and preparatory Grace,</hi> that puts the Heart into a fit temper to receive all other graces and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilments of Gods Spirit, and alſo to perform all other Duties and offices of Religion. <hi>Tria ſunt omnia,</hi> theſe <hi>All things</hi> here of a Chriſtians duty, are either ſuch as relate <hi>to our ſelves,</hi> or ſuch as relate <hi>to our God,</hi> or ſuch as relate <hi>to our Neighbour;</hi> (there cannot be named a Fourth) comprehended under the three titles of <hi>Sobriety, Piety,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus 2.12.</note> The Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to the practice of the <hi>two firſt</hi> Duties in the 7. verſe; Be <hi>ſober,</hi> watch unto <hi>prayer;</hi> but by a religious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if he had forgot himſelf, he ſeems to correct his miſtake with a <hi>But</hi> as in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But before <hi>ſobriety</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> that is, Before <hi>all</hi> things have charity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Before Sobriety.</hi> We cannot perform our duties to our <hi>own ſelves</hi> as we ought, nor acquire nor preſerve that Chriſtian calme temperature and due conſiſtence of our own ſpirits, before we firſt allay the ſtormes of variance, diſcord, and injuſtice towards our Brethren. <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Temperance,</hi> and <hi>Meekneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> and <hi>Contentation,</hi> and the like, are all <hi>Domeſtick graces,</hi> that conſtantly keep houſe in orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the private and particular affairs of our ſoules: <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> are <hi>publick graces</hi> that walk abroad in ordering our affections, and converſations towards our Brethren: and
<pb facs="tcp:171239:11"/> truly if we practice inſtead of Juſtice and Charity, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Malice, and Revenge towards our Brethren; our ſoules can enjoy no more inward and domeſtick peace in reſpect to the other graces of Sobriety under ſuch publick oppreſſions and revenges, then a private family can expect in the midſt of a Civil War; the publick blood, and violence, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine upon the innocent in City and Countrey, take away all the quiet and ſecurity from a mans own houſe: and it is no otherwiſe with a mans ſoul in reſpect to his Brother, if he once raiſeth the <hi>stormes</hi> of wrath in his heart, he muſt expect <hi>Fluctuations</hi> and <hi>Fomings</hi> upon the waters; and therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do as Chriſt did. Firſt, rebuke the <hi>windes,</hi> and then the <hi>Sea</hi> will ſoon be calm. Firſt allay thy tempeſtuous ſpirit towards thy Brother by the duty of Love and Charity, and then thou maiſt expect all the tranquil graces of ſobriety in thy own ſoul: Patience, Meekneſſe, Temperance, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and Humility, are gentle graces that grow only under the Wind and Sun, the tempeſts and bluſterings between Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſoon wither them. How did <hi>Ahabs</hi> choler againſt <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> turn his <hi>own</hi> ſtomach?<note place="margin">1 Kings 21.4.</note> 
               <hi>He could not eat bread,</hi> ſaith the Text, he was ſick becauſe he was angry, and he loſt his love and his health together: And truly as was this natural effect of wrath in him, ſuch is the ſpiritual effect of it in every Man; it turns the uncharitable Mans ſoul into a diſtemper, and as to thoſe private and perſonal graces of ſobriety, his conſtitution is thereby clearly altered, being truly (as we may ſay) ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, verifying the Wiſe mans Proverb in a ſpiritual ſence, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.30. <hi>That envie is the rottenneſſe of the bones;</hi> ſo was it with <hi>Ahab</hi> naturally, ſo is it with every malicious Man ſpiritually; it rots his ſoul, and corrupts and poyſons all his domeſtick graces of ſobriety: that whileſt he endeavours to work vengeance on his Brother, by the violence of his own impetuous ſpirit, he diſquiets and diſtempers, and therefore deſtroyes his own ſoul. As the Philoſopher ſaid of <hi>Charybdis,</hi> that it was <hi>Ipſius maris naufragium, &amp; quis ibi ſalvus ubi ipſum mare perit,</hi> a Gulf, where the waters moved with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that it ſeemed to be a ſhipwrack of the Sea it ſelf; and what ſhip can be ſafe there, where the Sea it ſelf is drownd?
<pb facs="tcp:171239:11"/> and truly ſuch is the violence of the malicious ſpirit; it is <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius animae naufragium,</hi> a torrent ſo violent, that it is a ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack to it ſelf, ſhattering and deſtroying him that would deſtroy his Brother: if therefore thou wouldeſt have thy own ſoul proſper in the perſonal graces of ſobriety, let thy ſpirit glide gently in all Offices of Love and Charity towards thy Brother. This is the <hi>firſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Before all things, that is, Before all duties of <hi>Sobriety</hi> have Charity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Before all things, that is, Before all duties of <hi>Piety, watch unto prayer,</hi> verſe 7. <hi>But before all things have charity.</hi> I need name no other place of Scripture for proof, but that very expreſſe doctrine of our Saviour in his Sermon upon the Mount, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.24. <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the altar, and there remember thy Brother hath ought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, leave there thy gift before the Altar, and go thy way,</hi> Firſt, <hi>be reconciled to thy Brother, and then come and offer thy gift:</hi> Forbear to tread in Gods Sanctuary, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach his Altars, until thou comeſt with feet ſhod with peace; all ſacrifices without this grace are like <hi>Cains</hi> that ſlew his Brother, a ſtink in Gods noſtrils.</p>
            <p>Its a proper trophy to bring <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſword into Gods houſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.9. The ſpoyles of Gods and his Churches incorrigible enemies, are matter of triumph and praiſe to God in the great Congregation: But to hang our <hi>Brothers</hi> ſword over Gods Altar, and to bring evil diſpoſitions of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and revenge againſt <hi>our Brother,</hi> when we come to crave mercy for <hi>our ſelves,</hi> what an unwarrantable preſumption is this? and how expreſly and ſadly do we ſue for our own condemnation, whileſt we pray, that <hi>God would forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſſe againſt us?</hi> Firſt therefore be reconciled, then come and offer thy gift: And in the Apoſtles order, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Follow peace,</hi> and then <hi>holineſſe;</hi> firſt, Peace with thy neighbour, then Holineſs to thy God. Malice is ſuch a <hi>Sowre Leaven</hi> that it ſowres the whole lump of Religious Duties; purge out <hi>firſt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Old Leaven, and then thy Hearing, and Reading, thy Meditations, and thy Prayers, and all will be according to the preparation of the Sanctuary: Which is the reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:171239:12"/> S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. exhorts Husband and Wife, to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of mutual love, correſpondence, and cohabitation, <hi>That their prayers be not hindred.</hi> And if I ſhould ſay that even <hi>Martyrdom</hi> it ſelf were but a vainglorious blaze, and a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe fool-hardineſſe without <hi>Love,</hi> I ſhould ſay no more then <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath ſaid before me, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>If I give my body to be burned and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God ſpake the ſame thing in Analogy to holy <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.8, 9, 10. when he told him that he ſhould <hi>not build</hi> Gods houſe, <hi>becauſe he had ſhed much blood, and made great warres;</hi> but his ſon ſhall be a Man of peace, his name ſhall be <hi>Solomon (peaceable)</hi> and he muſt build Gods houſe; If God would not eſteem his material Temple well built by hands dipt in blood, can we imagine he will accept of the ſpiritual and moſt ſacred Duties of Religion and Divine Worſhip performed with a <hi>heart</hi> ſtained with malice and revenge? He that is acceptably converſant in theſe holy things, muſt be a <hi>Solomon,</hi> a Man of peace and love towards his Brethren: therefore again, firſt, be reconciled before thou buildeſt Gods houſe, <hi>Watch unto prayer,</hi> but before this, and <hi>before all things have Charity.</hi> Thus you have ſeen how Charity goes before both duties of <hi>Sobriety</hi> towards our ſelves, and duties of <hi>Piety</hi> towards God, which is the <hi>firſt part</hi> of the importance of the duty, to wit, the <hi>Precedency</hi> of it, gathered from the Latine tranſlation of the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Before</hi> all things have charity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, come we to the other part of its Importance, to wit, its <hi>preheminence,</hi> drawn from the Engliſh Text <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Above</hi> all things have Charity, or, if you think this Good greek but ill tranſlated in this ſence, take the ſame doctrine in indubitable words from St. <hi>Paul Col.</hi> 3.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Above all things put on Charity;</hi> when it cannot be denied but the Apoſtle doth preach up the preheminence of this duty above all that went before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 133.</note>And truly when I conſider that holy <hi>David</hi> hath ſpent a whole Pſalm,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> a whole Chapter, upon no other ſubject then the <hi>excellency</hi> of this duty of Charity, I cannot thinke my ſelfe able to perform the ſame work in any Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171239:12"/> meaſure in a ſmall part of a Sermon; yet ſince it is fallen in our way, according to my time and talent, I ſhall ſhew you the <hi>preheminence</hi> of this duty above all others in theſe <hi>Foure</hi> particulars. In the <hi>perfection</hi> of its acts; In the <hi>ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of its nature; In the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> of its Influence, and laſtly, in the <hi>Duration</hi> of its Being.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is above all in the <hi>perfection</hi> of its acts.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>Now abideth Faith, Hope and Charity,</hi> theſe three; <hi>but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of theſe is Charity;</hi> The advancement of this grace will prove a very eaſie worke if we can ſet it above Faith it ſelfe; and ſince the holy Ghoſt hath ſaid it, we muſt make it good, and that in <hi>two</hi> particulars. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Charity is greater then Faith, in reſpect to the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of their acts, For Charity gives <hi>life,</hi> at leaſt it gives <hi>activity</hi> to Faith, and therefore is greater; read this aſſertion at large verified by <hi>St. Iames</hi> Chap. 2. from the 14. to the 23. <hi>Faith without works is dead;</hi> if <hi>a brother be naked or want Food,</hi> and ye <hi>ſay be be warmed and filled but give him nothing, what doth this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit? Faith is dead if it be alone; for the Devils beleeve and tremble,</hi> and v. 22. <hi>he</hi> ſaith that <hi>Abrahams faith wrought by works,</hi> and by <hi>works faith is perfect:</hi> And <hi>St. Paul</hi> makes up <hi>St. Iames</hi>'s argument by the ſpecification of thoſe works which actuate faith. <hi>Faith worketh by Love Gal.</hi> 5.6. It is love then which actuates, yea, which in <hi>St. Iames</hi> his phraſe, <hi>perfects</hi> faith; thus Charity is greater then Faith: <hi>firſt,</hi> in the <hi>efficacy</hi> of their acts, it actuates, it perfects faith. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> it is greater then faith in the <hi>Abſoluteneſs of its acts,</hi> Faith <hi>qua talis</hi> in its own nature implyeth <hi>imperfection,</hi> not only in matter of <hi>degrees</hi> (for ſo <hi>Charity</hi> alſo is imperfect in this life;) but even in its own <hi>kinde;</hi> the moſt perfect act of Faith, if it be <hi>but</hi> Faith, hath this imperfection in it, to wit, the <hi>Abſence</hi> of the object. For ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>It is of things not ſeen;</hi> whereas charity is the grace of union,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> and it is the careſſing of the heart in the actual Fruition of the object, and therefore is perfect in its own <hi>kinde;</hi> For which reaſon it abideth and Faileth not with Faith hope and other imperfect graces, which by reaſon of their imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are unfit for Heaven without a charge; as alſo are all
<pb facs="tcp:171239:13"/> thoſe that imply <hi>miſery</hi> in others, ſuch as pitty and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. which in the very natures of their acts, foreſpeak them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unfit for that ſtate where there is Fulneſs of joy for ever more; whereas this grace of Charity abideth the ſame in Heaven as on Earth in its <hi>kinde,</hi> (though in degrees it is more perfect) and for no other reaſon, but becauſe the acts and operations of Charity, even as they are performed here on Earth, do not imply any Eſſential inherent imperfections, which as you ſee, are to be found in all other graces: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Charity is <hi>Above</hi> all others, <hi>Firſt</hi> in the <hi>Perfection</hi> of its <hi>Acts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of its <hi>Nature,</hi> There is no duty of Religion that comes ſo neer to the delight of nature, as the duty of Brotherly love; as man is naturally a <hi>ſociable</hi> creature, ſo conſequently muſt he be as naturally a <hi>loving and affectionate</hi> creature, Love being the congregating and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting paſſion of the ſoule, whereby the object is drawn cloſe to the affection: ſo that Love ſimply in its own nature is the moſt conſonant to our natural inclination, even above all other duties of Religion whatſoever, which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> plainly intimates when he cryes out Pſal. 133.1. <hi>Behold how pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell together in unity:</hi> Faith, repentance, ſelf-denial, taking up the Croſs, and all duties of mortification, inſtead of pleaſure hold, in their very acts rather a diſpleaſure and contrariety to nature; but how pleaſant is unity among Brethren? wherefore above all other. <hi>Secondly</hi> in the ſweetneſs of its <hi>nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> of its influence, Charity tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth an univerſal vertue through the whole body of Gods worſhip and ſervice in all the duties of the ſame, if they are performed as they ought to be: whereas other duties are particularly ſtated within their own limits. <hi>Meditation</hi> is a diſtinct duty from <hi>hearing</hi> of the word preached; and <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is a diſtinct duty from <hi>prayer;</hi> and <hi>Receiving</hi> the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> diſtinct from both; but the duties of Love and Charity muſt have an univerſal influence in all. <hi>Charity</hi> being among the Graces much as <hi>Iustice</hi> among the vertues: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.14. The Apoſtle particularly exhorts the Corinthians to
<pb facs="tcp:171239:13"/> 
               <hi>Watchfulneſs,</hi> to <hi>magnanimity,</hi> to <hi>Conſtancy,</hi> in their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and diſtinct natures: but v. 14. he enjoyns Charity as an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> requiſite to the performance of theſe and all other <hi>particular</hi> duties whatſoever: <hi>Watch ye, Stand faſt</hi> in <hi>the Faith,</hi> quit <hi>you like men,</hi> be <hi>strong,</hi> here are the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar duties; and in the next <hi>verſe Let all things be done with Charity:</hi> like as it was under the law, an abundance of ſacrifices there were of proper and diſtinct kindes, ſome of <hi>Sheep,</hi> ſome of <hi>Bullocks,</hi> ſome of <hi>Lambs;</hi> ſome for <hi>peace,</hi> ſome for <hi>praiſe,,</hi> ſome for <hi>ſin;</hi> But all were kindled by the ſame holy fire, that was kept alwayes alive upon the holy Altar, for theſe ſeveral ſervices; And even thus is it with the grace of Charity, it is that holy Fire which is ever kept alive in the Altar of the good mans heart, whereby he enkindles all his evangelical ſacrifices which he offereth unto God; and therefore he that cometh with his gift to the altar, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be reconciled to his Brother, in effect expects to offer a burnt offering without Fire; let him leave his gift; <hi>Firſt</hi> Fetch this Fire, then let him kindle his Sacrifice, and perform the whole ſtate and ſeries of the duties of Religion, quickned with this common Catholick grace: which is to the other inferior duties of Gods worſhip, as the Sun is to the leſſer Stars, though they have a native beauty and light of their own, yet do they all borrow the chiefeſt part of their luſtre from this great ruling light of Charity. I need no better evidence of the univerſal influence of this grace, then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance the holy Pſalmiſt gives us <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.2. where he tells, us that the love of Brethren is that <hi>precious ointment</hi> of <hi>Aaron, which was poured upon his head, and ran down to his beard,</hi> and <hi>deſcended even to the skirts of his garments,</hi> and ſo gave a pleaſant tincture to every part of <hi>Aaron</hi> from head to foot: this diffuſive ointment, ſaith he, is the <hi>love and unity</hi> of <hi>Brethren,</hi> which gives a tincture to all the parts of <hi>Aaron,</hi> to the whole body of <hi>Gods worſhip</hi> and ſervice in all the duties of the ſame; not only to the participation of the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our ſalvation in the Sacraments, which is the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Aaron;</hi> but alſo to every quotidian meditation upon God, to every frequent admonition of our Brother, the <hi>skirts of Aaron,</hi> even all muſt ſmell of this precious ointment of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171239:14"/> wherefore it is above all others thirdly in the <hi>univerſality</hi> of its <hi>Influence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, In the <hi>Duration</hi> of its <hi>being,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity never faileth, but whether there be propheſies, they ſhal fail; whether there be tongues, they ſhall ceaſe; whether there be knowledge, it ſhall vaniſh away:</hi> All other both <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> muſt ſuffer a kinde of diſſolution before we can enter heaven; but charity never dies, continuing as immortal as the ſoul that bears it: Indeed we may ſay of the duration of all other graces, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpake of Mans <hi>Mortality,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. <hi>They ſhall not all die,</hi> but <hi>they ſhall be changed: Faith</hi> ſhall be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into <hi>viſion,</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> into <hi>fruition, Patience</hi> into <hi>triumph, Penitence</hi> into <hi>praiſe,</hi> &amp;c. But <hi>Charity</hi> ſhall not ſo much as undergo this <hi>change;</hi> for it ſhall be the ſame in its kinde, though greater in its degree, in Heaven as it was on the Earth; ſo that it is a grace that receives <hi>Enochs Tranſlation,</hi> without <hi>S. Pauls Mutation,</hi> paſſing into Heaven with us, and that without a change; no other graces do the like, and therefore <hi>above</hi> all others <hi>laſtly</hi> in the <hi>Duration</hi> of its being.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the <hi>Precedence</hi> and alſo the <hi>Preheminence</hi> of charity, and in both the <hi>Importance,</hi> which is the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of the Text from theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Before or above</hi> all <hi>things have charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to the <hi>Third part,</hi> to wit, from the <hi>Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> to the <hi>Complexion</hi> or <hi>Temperature</hi> of the duty, in theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſlated <hi>fervent</hi> charity. It is not every flaſh of <hi>friendſhip,</hi> nor formal fit of <hi>courtſhip</hi> that is the charity; extold by the Apoſtle, but it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fervent charity; which if we will take the advantages of the original without reſtraining our ſelves to the tranſlation, we ſhall finde it as fit a word for our purpoſe, as can be found in the whole trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of the Greek tongue: For it is <hi>one</hi> word, which, in the force of the ſeveral conſtructions it uſually bears, gives us all the moſt requiſite Dimenſions or Admeaſurements of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity, to wit, both the <hi>Extenſion, Intention,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being uſed frequently in all three ſences, as you ſhall ſee in the purſuit of each particular. 1. It intimates that Chriſtian charity muſt be an extended charity towards
<pb facs="tcp:171239:14"/> all for the <hi>Bredth</hi> of it. 2. That it muſt be an Intended or intenſe, or fervent charity proceeding from the ſincerity of the heart, for the <hi>depth</hi> of it. 3. That it muſt be alſo a protended <hi>(i. e.)</hi> a laſting, a continued charity, not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by any perſonal diſobligements whatſoever, for the <hi>Length</hi> of it: as if Providence had fitted it only for this place, as if it were an <hi>Adjective</hi> made on purpoſe for this <hi>ſubſtantive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, if our charity muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, then it muſt be an <hi>extended and an enlarged</hi> charity even unto all, which we muſt needs confeſſe is the native and moſt literal conſtruction of the word, which is originally compounded of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifying literally to <hi>Extend or enlarge in breadth,</hi> or to ſtretch forth to a great diſtance; in this ſence is it uſed by S. <hi>Luke</hi> Acts 26.1. Then <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtretched forth the hand, and anſwered for himſelf: ſo is it likewiſe uſed by S. <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.31. ſuddenly Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtretching forth his hand, &amp;c. ſaved <hi>Peter</hi> from ſinking: An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably therefore if true charity is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it muſt be a ſtretched forth and an enlarged charity. <q rend="margQuotes">True Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity therefore enjoyned in this Apoſtolick precept is not a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor incloſed affection, impaled onely within the bounds of narrow relations either natural or contracted, as of Countrey, Friends, Benefactors, Kindred, or the like; but it is a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne and a Common Grace, knowing no other bounds or limits but the univerſal relation in which all men ſtand towards God, who is the common cauſe in whom all concenter and agree:</q> and this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>extended charity,</hi> practiſed to the full by our Saviour Chriſt, who ſet us copies as well as impoſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and taught us by his Example as well as by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; in whoſe life I know not any generation of people whom he excluded from the charity of his miracles: The <hi>Centurion,</hi> a Roman; the <hi>Woman</hi> at the <hi>Well-head,</hi> a Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan; the <hi>Woman,</hi> that interceded for her Daughter, a Dog a Syrophenician; the <hi>churliſh Gadarene;</hi> the <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican; the <hi>Lepers;</hi> the <hi>Demonaick;</hi> the <hi>Deaf;</hi> the <hi>Dumb;</hi> the <hi>Blinde;</hi> the <hi>Lame;</hi> the <hi>Sick;</hi> and the <hi>Dead:</hi> all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſexes, conditions, and ages of Men, did partake of the benefit of his <hi>extended</hi> love, giving in theſe outward Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb facs="tcp:171239:15"/> Symbols of the love of Chriſt ſpiritually to mankinde in the ſalvation of their ſouls; <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. <hi>The love of God hath appeared unto</hi> all <hi>men:</hi> and Chap. 3. verſe 4. <hi>The love of Chriſt towards</hi> Man <hi>appeared:</hi> he was (as <hi>Themiſtius</hi> ſaith a good King ſhould be) neither <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; not a friend onely to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> nor yet to the houſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> not to the Jewes his Brethren after the fleſh, theſe are too narrow relations for ſuch a bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe charity; but his Love towards <hi>Man</hi> appeared, which is a ſpecifick denomination applicable to Turks, to Negroes, to Indians, to all that own the title of Reaſonable Creatures; even to all the Genealogies of our Anceſtors from <hi>Adam</hi> to this Age,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.4.</note> that now lie buried in the land of forgetfulneſſe, for Chriſt is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the God that <hi>was;</hi> to all that now breathe upon the face of Gods earth; for Chriſt is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the God that <hi>is;</hi> and to all that ever ſhall be to the laſt diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, for he is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the God that is <hi>to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly, his <hi>precept</hi> of Love is as <hi>large</hi> as his <hi>practiſe.</hi> Its true, the tenor of the Law in S. <hi>Luke</hi> 10.27. is, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> as if Strangers and Enemies were excluded from the Obligation of this Precept: but S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the beſt Interpreter of Chriſts Doctrine, rehearſing the ſame Law, Rom. 13.8. ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>He that loveth</hi> another <hi>hath fulfilled the Law:</hi> it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not our Friend, our Companion, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, but he that loveth <hi>another</hi> man, any Man. It is not private intereſt, party, nor faction, that can impound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity within any particular ſtate or condition of Men, but it loves all in the capacity of God and Religion, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing up into its immenſity all the leſſer and limited chanels, of love, ariſing from the narrow endeerments of nature or converſation, ſuch as are Kindred, Friends, or Benefactors, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly, if you would ſee both <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> in one inſtance, you may finde them in <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. where when it was told Chriſt that his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Brethen</hi> after the fleſh <hi>ſtood without to ſpeak with him,</hi> he anſwered verſ 48. <hi>Who is my mother, and who are my brethren?</hi> alas you ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:171239:15"/> after the manner of Men, and make an <hi>encloſure</hi> of that affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction within the limits of Nature, which I intend ſhould be a Campaigne and a Common Field even for the benefit of the whole world, through the univerſality of grace; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Text, yes and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo, he ſtretched forth both his <hi>Hand</hi> and his <hi>Heart</hi> towards his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Matthew,</hi>) towards the whole <hi>multitude,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Mark,</hi>) and ſaid even of this multitude, <hi>Behold my mother and brethren:</hi> why and how ſo? <hi>Whoſoever doth the will of my Father, the ſame is my Brother, Siſter, and Mother;</hi> there is little queſtion but in that croud there were ſome of very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and remote conditions, and perhaps of different cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates; ſeldom a croud in Chriſts time, but was ſuch, by reaſon of the mixture of other nations with the Jewes, under the Regency of the Romans: yet whether they were Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian or Scythian, Bond, or Free, Jew or Gentile, Chriſt is all <hi>to,</hi> and <hi>in</hi> all:<note place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> That ſpiritual relation in which they ſtand to his heavenly Father, by an upright life and due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his will, adopts Chriſtians of the moſt remote condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be his Mother and Brethren. There being very little queſtion but Chriſts <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in this place is of the ſame latitude as S. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Wherefore if we will either obey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt; or imitate the <hi>practice</hi> of Chriſt, our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity muſt be univerſal and extended according to his who hath required us to love one another, even as he hath loved us. We read of ſomewhat a ſtrange argument which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle uſeth to the <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.2. to perſwade them to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hoſpitality of ſtrangers; <hi>For thereby</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>ſome have entertained Angels unawares:</hi> If we conſider our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in that condition he ſtands towards God, even ſo all Men are ſtrangers unto us; and unleſſe we had the peruſal of the <hi>Book of Life,</hi> we know not who will make a veſſel of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> or who of <hi>Diſhonour.</hi> Let me therefore exhort you in the Apoſtles phraſe to entertain into your affections all thoſe that are ſo much ſtrangers to you, leſt you chance to ſhut out of your charity one of Gods <hi>Angels,</hi> one that hath the ſecret ſignature of <hi>election</hi> upon him; and then Chriſt come at laſt to you, and ſay as to thoſe unkinde and uncharitable
<pb facs="tcp:171239:16"/> wretches in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.45. <hi>In as much as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me.</hi> Therefore let your charity be in the firſt place, an <hi>extended</hi> charity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if it be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it muſt be a deep, intenſe, and <hi>fervent</hi> charity, ſuch as proceeds from the very bottom of the <hi>Heart,</hi> and the integrity of <hi>our Souls;</hi> (which being the main part of the duty, and withal the expreſſe language of the Text, it will be neceſſary that we inſiſt longer upon this conſtruction, then upon either of the other two.) I confeſſe I finde this word not often uſed in this ſence elſewhere in holy Writ: But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is an Adverb of the ſame Verb is frequent in Greek Authors, ſignifying <hi>Impensè, vehementer &amp; totis viribus;</hi> to do a thing <hi>Earneſtly, Vehemently,</hi> and with <hi>utmoſt Induſtry,</hi> which is in effect the ſame with <hi>Fervently</hi> in the Text; expreſſing that true zeal and ſincerity of affection which one Man ought to have to another. <q rend="margQuotes">True Chriſtian charity is neither a cold neighbourhood, nor a formal courtſhip, nor a vainglorious beneficence; but it is the intire and zealous affection of the very ſoul.</q> Expreſſed by S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 12.10. in a phraſe beyond the reach of our Engliſh tongue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, where he requires that one Man ſhould love another with the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with the ſame <hi>natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> as a Mother loves the childe of her own bowels, which in our tranſlation we call a <hi>kinde affection, Be kindly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned one towards another with brotherly love:</hi> which though it fall far ſhort of the Original, yet ſpeaks enough to tell us that the <hi>Heart</hi> is the principal Requiſite in charity; and that that Philoſophers compaſſion was no better then Stoical hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, who whileſt he allowed his friend to contribute ſad lookes and language to the diſtreſſed and miſerable, reſtrains him with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Epicter.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſure take heed lest thou ſuffer any inward compaſſion for him;</hi> turning this moſt tender affection of the heart, into a formal counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit compliance of the outward behaviour, clear contrary to the nature of Chriſtianity, which is of ſuch a pure and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual extraction, that although we read of rewards upon the performance of no duties more, then for works of <hi>Charity,</hi> ſuch as relieving the oppreſſed, feeding the hungry, clothing the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171239:16"/> naked, bewailing and comforting the miſerable, and other the <hi>external</hi> acts of charity; yet is neither this, nor any other duties of Religion accepted or rewarded by God for their own ſakes, but only according to the inward affection of the ſoul from whence they proceed.</p>
            <p>Indeed a man might think, that if there were any outward acts of obedience accepted for themſelves, they ſhould be the outward offices of <hi>Charity</hi> towards our Brethren, and the plauſible reaſon might be; Becauſe how ever they may proceed from a <hi>wrong Ayme,</hi> yet they do unfallibly hit the <hi>right marke,</hi> and fulfil the immediate, and indeed, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end of thoſe acts, and that is, the relief of our needy Brother: For doubtleſs the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Sheep</hi> &amp;c. would have yielded David and his men as wholſome refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had they come from the hand of <hi>Churliſh Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.18.</note> as they did coming as the preſent of a chearful and <hi>generous Abigail.</hi> So that <hi>operative Charity</hi> conſiſting in that order it beares to our <hi>Brothers</hi> good; if our needy brother be benefited by the <hi>outward act,</hi> it is accidental as to the <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> whether that act proceed from an inward princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Grace, Nature,</hi> or <hi>Luſt;</hi> wherefore, I ſay, if any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts of obedience were of themſelves acceptable, one might think they ſhould be thoſe of <hi>Charity</hi> towards our <hi>Brother:</hi> For as for thoſe of piety and worſhip towards God; ſuch as <hi>Watching, Fasting, Praying, Hearing, Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting:</hi> and the like external acts of Religion, the intire order that theſe hold in the ſtate of our obedience is only to ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ends and purpoſes; and therefore although we are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to worſhip and glorifie God in our <hi>Bodies</hi> and in our <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> which are Gods. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. Yet God himſelf being a moſt <hi>pure spirit,</hi> unto which all theſe outward acts of piety and worſhip tend, and in whom they fully <hi>End;</hi> it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very improper to the nature of them, that they ſhould be accepted in and for themſelves, but only as they derive a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout influence from, and have an original dependance upon the ſincerity and zeal of the Inner man, and the ſpirit from whence they proceed. For doubtleſs that argument of our Saviour drawen from the nature of that God we ſerve <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.
<pb facs="tcp:171239:17"/> 24. is unanſwerable when he ſaith, <hi>That God is a Spirit, and therefore muſt be worſhipped in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> Wherefore, to return to our purpoſe, although Relief and Brotherly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply is the whole End of <hi>operative Charity</hi> conſiſting in the outward offices of Love, which is ſufficiently ſatisfied if thoſe offices are performed, yet if we take the duty of Chriſtian charity in the <hi>whole ſtate</hi> of the duty, and not by parcel-meals, we ſhall finde that <hi>operative charity</hi> is not the half part of that required in this precept of Love; for this, as all duties of the <hi>Second Table,</hi> hath a double reſpiciency in it, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate reſpect is towards our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> the ultimate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is towards <hi>God:</hi> which is a conſideration that makes the duties of love to become offices of piety to God as well as of charity to our Brother.</p>
            <p>Now looking upon this duty in its <hi>immediate</hi> reſpect to our Neighbour, I confeſſe if <hi>Gods</hi> Law were to be conſidered no otherwiſe then the <hi>Statute Lawes</hi> of the Land, which for the ſubſtance of the precepts forbid the very ſame par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars as are expreſſed in the <hi>Second Table,</hi> as <hi>Rebellion, Murder, Theft, Adultery, Falſe witneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> and enjoynes alſo the ſame duties of Juſtice and Charity to our Brethren: Now, I ſay, if <hi>Gods</hi> Law reached no further then <hi>Mans,</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative charity would fulfil the whole duty, Mans Law look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no farther then to the reſtraining or enjoyning the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing Gods Law ought to be conſidered, as the firſt Law written in our hearts, and the Law of Nature as well as of God; in this conſideration the <hi>inward principle</hi> of thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of love from whom they proceed, muſt be conſidered as well as the external acts themſelves; for as much as God at the firſt did ſo abſolutely and to all purpoſes inſtruct and furniſh our natures, that look whatever outward duty he required at our hands, he placed an anſwerable principle in our hearts to incline and carry us through the performance of that work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us; as conceiving it to be too ſevere a uſage of man, above all other works of the creation beſides, to require him to do that duty, unto which God had not firſt imprinted a propenſion in his nature, as to command him the outward of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices
<pb facs="tcp:171239:17"/> of <hi>Society</hi> and <hi>Hoſpitality</hi> without giving him the inward principle of love; or the duties of <hi>ſuccouring</hi> the diſtreſſed, or <hi>relieving</hi> the needy, without the inward principle of pitty and commiſeration, and ſo in all the reſt.</p>
            <p>And truly, though I deny not, but many a good almes hath been given for vainglory, to be ſeen of Men; many through the importunity of our needy Brother; and many through cuſtome; yet theſe are not <hi>natural,</hi> but <hi>equivocal</hi> productions of charity; much like the generations of <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Flies,</hi> and other Inſects, which are often ingendred of putrefaction, and not from their own kindes, which we call <hi>Imperfect Generations</hi> in Philoſophy: Even ſuch <hi>unkindly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions</hi> are ſuch ſorts of good works in the Law of Charity, that come beſides the common order of Nature: God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore originally not only enjoyning <hi>the Act,</hi> but adminiſtring the proper <hi>and univocal principle</hi> of that act in the ſpirit of Man: By the Law of Nature rectified, we are required to take both into conſideration; and not onely to be <hi>hoſpitable</hi> to our Brethren, but alſo to <hi>love</hi> them; not onely to <hi>help</hi> the miſerable, but alſo to <hi>pity</hi> and compaſſionate them; ſo that the inward fervency of the ſpirit in works of charity is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the <hi>firſt</hi> place <hi>Nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſitate principii,</hi> as Natures proper <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> principle for ſuch acts.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, if we look upon charity as reflecting upon <hi>God,</hi> we ſhall finde yet more cauſe why this fervency of the heart is requiſite in this duty. Becauſe in this capacity it is a duty <hi>of piety,</hi> as all other duties of Religion and worſhip are, which have their outward acts (as I have ſaid) purely in order to inward and ſpiritual purpoſes, and grateful onely as they proceed from ſincere and ſpiritual principles. Now that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity bears ſuch a reflection upon God, and therefore becomes as it were a duty of the <hi>Firſt Table,</hi> is intimated by the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.31. where it is ſaid, <hi>That he that oppreſſeth the poor reproacheth his Maker;</hi> not only by his act of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence againſt the poſitive Law of God, who by adding to this duty his divine ſanction, made that <hi>moral</hi> which was at firſt <hi>natural,</hi> whereby you ſee the Heart is likewiſe neceſſary in this duty. Secondly, <hi>Neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate praecepti;</hi> but alſo reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:171239:18"/> his Maker, in reſpect to that order and relation in which they ſtand towards God, having a ſupreme intereſt in all men, but eſpecially in the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy,</hi> and of theſe chiefly in them, who together with their outward indigencies are poor in <hi>ſpirit</hi> alſo; of whom Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40. <hi>In as much as ye have done it unto the leaſt of theſe my brethren, ye have done it unto me.</hi> Now if offices of love and charity to our Brethren be performed to God, and to Chriſt himſelf; we knowing whom we ſerve, know likewiſe our charity muſt be affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and fervent as well as operative, and that as you ſee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly <hi>Neceſſitate medii,</hi> as a proper means of ſervice anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that <hi>God</hi> we <hi>ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Away then 1. With <hi>Negative Friendſhips,</hi> and <hi>Cold Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhoods,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the univerſal practice of this uncharitable Age, wherein Men think they diſcharge their duties ſufficiently in this Law of Love, if they do <hi>no</hi> wrong, and offer <hi>no</hi> violence, and are <hi>not</hi> profeſſed Enemies: alas, this is too cold a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for this hot climate of Love; true charity is a grace that puts the heart of a Chriſtian into a fermentation, and a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent working of the bowels upon our Brethren: for Love <hi>leavens</hi> the ſoul, as well as Malice, and there is a heat in both, only the one is by a fire from <hi>Hell,</hi> and the other from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: But this cold indifferency hangs between theſe two fires, like the middle Region between Heaven and Earth, in a perpetual froſt, having neither celeſtial grace enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindle the kindly warmth of love; nor infernal malice, nor miſchief enough, or at leaſt not courage, or opportunity, or provocation enough, to blow up the fiery combuſtions of wrath and revenges. And yet with ſhame we may ſpeak it if we look into City and Countrey, we ſhall finde this degree of charity to be all that is practiſed in obedience to the whole precept of love; Nothing but a bare <hi>Non-enmity,</hi> and a <hi>Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive friendſhip, not fighting, not revenging, not provoking, not injuring,</hi> and this is all: which is a diſpoſition that gives to Man but one remove from Wolves, and Beares, for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not love one minute or ſcruple leſſe then this degree, but we muſt degenerate into plain Savages, and exerciſe profeſt acts of cruelty and hoſtility one againſt another. And yet we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171239:18"/> think, if we can ſpeak in the Phariſees dialect, <hi>Not</hi> an <hi>Extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, not</hi> a <hi>Murderer, not</hi> an <hi>Enemy,</hi> we ſhall be juſtified in this law of love, and that we are friends ſufficient to our Brethren.</p>
            <p>Which is the more to be lamented, becauſe it ſeems to be not onely a <hi>defect</hi> in our <hi>practice,</hi> but alſo an <hi>error</hi> of our <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as appears by our behaviour in moſt ſolemn and ſacred ſeverities, to wit, in thoſe great adminiſtrations of Religion which call for an exact view and examination of every Mans ſoul, ſuch as are the holy Sacraments: Wherein Men do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all their ſpiritual labour to approve their <hi>Faith</hi> to be lively and efficacious, and their <hi>repentance</hi> to be truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble; their mortifications to be truly <hi>mental</hi> in ſubduing their luſts, and not only in disfiguring their faces, and uſing corporal ſeverities. But in this ſpiritual ſurveigh, when they conſider themſelves in this duty of charity; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps if they are at open defiance and profeſſed variance with any Man, they will think it fit to skin over this feſtering ſore with a falſe formal reconciliation; but if you examine their charity as to the reſt of their Brethren, they'l ſay, <q rend="margQuotes">They bear them no ill will, they never did them any injuries or wrongs either in perſon, goods, or good names, they never med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nor made with them, and they are enemies to no Man living;</q> and this is the cold negative account they give of their duty towards their Brother, whom God commands them to love with as fervent an affection as they <hi>love themſelves:</hi> whereas if they ſhould be thus negative in the accounts of their other graces, inſtead of coming with their <hi>wedding garments</hi> to <hi>Gods Table,</hi> they would come <hi>ſtark naked.</hi> If thy <hi>Faith</hi> ſhould be onely a belief, that thou ſhouldeſt be ſaved, <hi>not</hi> by <hi>Baal, not</hi> by the Idols of the <hi>Heathen, not</hi> by the <hi>Turks Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet, not</hi> by the Jewes <hi>Talmud, not</hi> by the Papiſts <hi>Legends</hi> and <hi>Traditions:</hi> And thy <hi>Repentance</hi> ſhould be only a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary <hi>forbearance</hi> of the acts of ſin, a <hi>not being</hi> drunk, or <hi>not</hi> ſwearing, or <hi>not</hi> ſtealing, or the like. But whileſt thou art ſufficiently convinced in thy judgement, that thy <hi>faith ſhould</hi> be <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>lively,</hi> and a <hi>firm belief</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt is thy Saviour, relying with a bold and lively affiance of thy heart, upon his promiſes for life and ſalvation: and alſo that thy <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171239:19"/> ſhould be truly <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>contrite,</hi> both a <hi>compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and ſorrow of ſoul for ſins paſt, and a <hi>pious purpoſe</hi> of the heart never to commit the like ſins again: yet in this fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent duty of <hi>charity,</hi> if thou canſt ſay I have done <hi>no</hi> Man wrong, and bear them <hi>no</hi> ill will, and am an <hi>enemy</hi> to <hi>no</hi> man living, thou thinkeſt in thy own judgement that thou haſt ſaid enough: we may call this indeed a <hi>putting off</hi> of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>profeſſed enmity:</hi> But it is not, as the Apoſtle requires <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. A <hi>putting on of charity;</hi> but it is a miſerable and a forlorn <hi>denudation</hi> of the ſoul, and a ſtripping it ſtark naked: whereas charity, if it be well put on, is a Garment that keeps him <hi>warm</hi> that wears it; that heart ſhall never feel the <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>negative friendſhips,</hi> that is truly furniſhed with the grace of <hi>fervent</hi> charity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, away with the falſe and deceitful <hi>charity of the Tongue,</hi> practiſed in Court and Countrey, by all who are more liberal of <hi>good words,</hi> then either of <hi>good wiſhes</hi> or <hi>good deeds,</hi> who when their brethrens neceſſities require either their <hi>purſe, counſel, favour,</hi> or <hi>intereſt</hi> to help them out of their preſent diſtreſſe; preſently (in the Apoſtles phraſe) they fall to tuning their <hi>tinkling Cymbals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.1.</note> and give them a liberal <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of all former favours, and how joyful they ſhould be to make a grateful return of ſo much kindneſſe, and profeſſe their readineſſe to do them any ſervice that lies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of their powers; with much more of this <hi>French charity.</hi> But when it comes to the point <hi>of aſſiſtance,</hi> they begin to bewail their unhappineſſe that they are not able to ſerve them in this one requeſt, either their <hi>money</hi> is out of the way, or their <hi>favour</hi> is eclipſed and <hi>intereſt</hi> abated, or twenty pretended <hi>occaſions</hi> of importance draw them another way: and thus they ſtretch out the expectation of their nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy brethren, with nothing but the winde of fair words, and leave them as helpleſſe as they found them: Nay, perhaps at that very time are contriving and meditating ſecret ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, how to <hi>over-reach</hi> or <hi>undermine</hi> them in thoſe very af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in which they craved their aſſiſtance: which is no new piece of Courtſhip among great ones, that uſe more <hi>flatteries</hi> to their friends then <hi>Fucaſſes</hi> to their faces; whereas indeed
<pb facs="tcp:171239:19"/> the one can be call'd no more true <hi>charity,</hi> then the other true <hi>beauty:</hi> Holy <hi>David</hi> was troubled with ſuch Courtiers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.13. <hi>Mine equal, my guide, my acquaintance—His words were ſmoother then butter, and ſofter then oyl, when war was in his heart,</hi> verſe 21. Which practice is ſo far from <hi>fervent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> that 'tis <hi>fervent malice</hi> and <hi>fervent envy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are, guilty of a more harmleſſe ſort of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that will give nothing but the cheap almes of good words to him that asks &amp; needs out of the chargeableneſs of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: like S. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Eleemoſynaries, James</hi> 2.16. that ſay to the <hi>naked</hi> and to the <hi>hungry, be ye warmed, and be ye filled,</hi> but neither give <hi>food</hi> nor <hi>raiment;</hi> alaſſe what do words profit them? Breath indeed is a <hi>cheap dole,</hi> but 'tis <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> it may <hi>cool</hi> the naked, but it cannot <hi>clothe</hi> him: and winde may <hi>ſwell</hi> the hungry with a falſe expectation, but it cannot <hi>feed</hi> him. There are no words that perform the ends of charity, but his, who ſpake <hi>the word</hi> and Iſrael <hi>had bread</hi> from Heaven, and <hi>garments</hi> that were not old by wearing; even the word of him that <hi>feeds the Ravens,</hi> and <hi>clothes the Lilies,</hi> by whoſe Word we live more then <hi>by our own bread, Matth.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Let us therefore love not in word nor in tongue, but in deed, and in truth,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>In deed,</hi> that our charity may be <hi>profitable,</hi> and in <hi>truth,</hi> that our charity may be <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere</hi> and <hi>fervent.</hi> Therefore away in the ſecond place with the comfortleſſe <hi>charity of the Tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, if true charity muſt be fervent, Away with the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>extended</hi> charity of <hi>the Hand,</hi> the charity of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> that give onely <hi>to be ſeen of men;</hi> who although many a poor ſoul may have been <hi>refreſhed</hi> by their <hi>Almes,</hi> &amp; <hi>clothed</hi> in their <hi>Liveries,</hi> and <hi>recovered</hi> by their <hi>Phyſick;</hi> yet at the laſt account they will find, they had as good never have given at all, as have given at the <hi>ſound of a Trumpet</hi> for vain-glory and applauſe, without any true ſincere charity in their ſoules. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar be it from me to ſpeak againſt the poor mans intereſt; God knowes he lives in <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>rags,</hi> notwithſtanding all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>incomes</hi> of <hi>charity,</hi> yea, though we take in thoſe alſo which <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>portunity</hi> or <hi>custome,</hi> which <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>vain-glory,</hi> or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ariſaical <hi>motives</hi> of beneficence may bring into the poor
<pb facs="tcp:171239:20"/> mans Store-houſe. I onely tell the rich the beſt way to huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band their charity, and that they may at the ſame rate, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to their own hearts and conſciences, the true ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſtian and religious benefactours,</hi> as they now give to buy onely the ayre of a <hi>good name</hi> and the vain reputation of <hi>munificence.</hi> It is but onely altering the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> of the <hi>Heart,</hi> the <hi>Hand</hi> hath already learn'd its duty. And unleſſe the heart be changed, you may call it <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>oſtentation,</hi> but you exceedingly wrong this ſweet and ſpiritual grace of Chriſtianity to call it <hi>charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if this ſeems a <hi>myſtery</hi> and a <hi>ſoloeciſme</hi> againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon dialect of the World, to deny <hi>almes-deeds</hi> to be <hi>charity,</hi> go and learn the meaning of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Paradox, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>That a man may give all his goods to feed the poor, and yet have no charity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 4.</note> Or what think you of <hi>Jaels</hi> kindneſſe to <hi>Siſera?</hi> who brings her <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Butter</hi> in a <hi>Lordly D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh</hi> to the faint and the weary Captain, and gives him houſe and harbour, entertainment, and lodging; if we did not ſee the <hi>Nail</hi> and the <hi>Hammer</hi> we ſhould be ready enough to call this <hi>pure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion:</hi> but when we read of the <hi>fatal effect</hi> of this kindneſſe, how ſhould we wrong the integrity and ſimplicity of this lovely grace, to give to ſuch uſages the name of <hi>charity?</hi> And when I conſider how many <hi>Jaels favours</hi> are <hi>beſtowed</hi> in the World, only upon a deſigne to work in Men the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of their fidelity, that ſo they might deſtroy with the greater aſſurance and advantage, I cannot but think it high time to preach up the charity of the <hi>heart:</hi> and to tell you that the liberality of the <hi>hand alone,</hi> is nothing but the <hi>price</hi> of <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> nay, perhaps, it may be the very <hi>pretexts</hi> of <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery,</hi> a piece of charity which the Devil practiſed, who had good nature enough to offer Chriſt the <hi>glories</hi> of the world, when he ſuffered <hi>hunger</hi> and <hi>ſolitude</hi> in the waſte wilderneſſe: and the <hi>ſame foul</hi> ſpirit that once thought to make <hi>Job curſe God</hi> by <hi>Taking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 1.11. Chap. 2.5.</note> now tryes whether he can make our Saviour <hi>bleſſe</hi> the Devil by <hi>Giving.</hi> And even ſuch, and no other, are the deceitful charities of the <hi>Hand,</hi> where the <hi>Heart</hi> is not ſincere and upright: and thus much for <hi>reprehenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Now in one word of <hi>Exhortation;</hi> if Charity muſt bee <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:171239:20"/> Bee yee then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>kindly affectioned one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with brotherly love;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> reſt not in the cold formalities of <hi>vulgar freindſhip,</hi> nor in the outward <hi>complements,</hi> or uncertain offices <hi>of Love;</hi> but let your hearts erne over your brothers neceſſities, and <hi>fellow-feele</hi> in all their miſeries: doutleſs Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion makes Charity a very ſecret and mentall grace, when it's call'd in Scripture by the name of <hi>Bowels,</hi> Col 3.12. <hi>Put on therefore</hi> (as <hi>the elect of God holy and beloved,) Bowels of mercy:</hi> and in another place, to ſhew us whence every outward act of Charity ſhould proceed, the denyall of aſſiſtance to the poor and needy is called <hi>a ſhutting up of our Bowels.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.17. <hi>Whoſo hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother hath need, and ſhutteth up his bowels of compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> the holy Ghoſt in this place takes no notice of any of thoſe <hi>equivocal productions</hi> of Charity, which may proceed either from <hi>custome, importunity</hi> or <hi>vain-glory;</hi> account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ourward office of Love worth naming, but what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from <hi>open bowels,</hi> that is, from a Chriſtian <hi>tender compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of our Brethrens needs. If yee wil but change the name and call <hi>Charity, Love;</hi> you will ſoon ſee the neceſſity of the <hi>heart</hi> in this duty: love being an affection ever naturally fixed and ſeated there; and it is as improper for men to <hi>love</hi> with their <hi>hands,</hi> or to <hi>love</hi> with their <hi>tongues,</hi> as it is to <hi>ſee</hi> with their <hi>ears,</hi> or <hi>hear</hi> with their <hi>eyes.</hi> Which <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>ſacred</hi> ſeat of this divine grace, the holy Apoſtle evidently diſcovers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. Where hee calls it Charity out of a <hi>pure heart,</hi> a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> and <hi>faith unfained:</hi> Outward offices of love, where they are found alone, are but Charity's out of <hi>uncleane hands,</hi> but the true Apoſtolical Chriſtian Love, is Charity out of a <hi>prue heart:</hi> Excellently expreſſed by God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.10. where he calls it a <hi>drawing out of the ſoul to the hungry;</hi> it is not ſo much a drawing out of our treaſures, our <hi>cruiſe,</hi> and our <hi>Barrel,</hi> but wee muſt ſet our ſouls on broach, and draw out even the ſecret compaſſions, and ernings of our own bowells over the neceſſities of our needy brethren; and by this means how ſlender and narrow ſoever thy <hi>ſhare</hi> is of the good things of this World, thou ſhalt diſcover a rich <hi>fountain</hi> of Love, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to anſwer all the <hi>neceſſities</hi> of thy brethren; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:171239:21"/> 
               <hi>treaſures</hi> may bee exhauſted, and the <hi>cruiſe</hi> may fail, and the <hi>barrell</hi> ceaſe, but the overflowing Fountain of <hi>Chriſtian pitty,</hi> and compaſſion in the good mans heart, ſhall never bee drawn dry; for ſo ſaith the Text, v. 11. <hi>If thou draw out thy ſoul to the hungry, then thou ſhalt bee as a ſpring of waters, whoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters fayl not:</hi> which leads us to the laſt conſtruction of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>protended</hi> or laſting Charity.</p>
            <p>Which is the third <hi>dimenſion</hi> of this grace, to wit, the <hi>length</hi> of it. True Chriſtian Charity to our brother, doth not live and die with our own ends and intereſts, it doth not laſt till our turnes are ſerved, nor ceaſe upon any perſonal indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or diſobligements, but it is in the Philoſophers phraſe, <hi>pertinax bonitas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec.</note> a grace, which as no worldly inducements <hi>wrought</hi> in us, ſo no worldly diſcouragement, can <hi>blaſt,</hi> but it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>laſting</hi> and <hi>perpetual</hi> Charity; which conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the word, I need not crave aide of profane Authors to juſtifie, though <hi>Suidas</hi> and others frequently uſe it for <hi>jugis</hi> and <hi>aſſiduus;</hi> but I can give you expreſs Scripture for it, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.5. <hi>Peter</hi> was kept in Priſon, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. it is not tranſlated <hi>fervent</hi> prayer, But <hi>Prayer without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing was made by the Church to God for him:</hi> and if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bee <hi>Prayer without ceaſing,</hi> ſurely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may bee tranſlated, as well, <hi>Charity without ceaſing,</hi> not concluded by our own intereſts or our Brothers diſcourteſies, but it ought to bee a perpetual and a durable duty, like our Saviours, who when he loves us once, hee loves us unto the end, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The cauſe of all the diſſolutions or corruptions of <hi>natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> ariſeth from the fighting and victory of <hi>contrary princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> which is the reaſon we ſay in Philoſophy, That God who is a <hi>ſimple being</hi> muſt needs be <hi>Eternal.</hi> Now though <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> charity like <hi>natural</hi> bodies, is deſtroy'd by contraries, by an <hi>unworthy reproach,</hi> or an <hi>ungrateful return,</hi> or an <hi>uncivil affront,</hi> or any other perſonal injury; yet that charity which is a Chriſtian grace, is exercis'd and improv'd by ſuch tryals; it can take <hi>pleaſure in reproaches,</hi> and <hi>joy in perſecutions;</hi> it can <hi>love enemies,</hi> and <hi>bleſſe perſecutors,</hi> and <hi>pray for the ſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and malicious</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and therefore the next word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7, 8. It <hi>ſuffereth All
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:171239:21"/> things, it endureth All things,</hi> and therefore it followes, <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity never faileth:</hi> and how can we imagine that any thing can deſtroy that which even <hi>Enemies improve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly God and Nature ſeem to have conſpired to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> make this grace perpetuall; In differences of <hi>Religions</hi> we ſay <hi>Nulli ſunt taliter diſcrepantes, &amp;c.</hi> No Men are of ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions, but they agree in ſome common principles, out of which arguments may be drawn to bring all at laſt to unity of judgement in the ſame truth. Thus the <hi>Christian</hi> and the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> agree in the Book of Nature; the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and the <hi>Jew</hi> in the Old Teſtament, and the Reformed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and the <hi>Papiſt</hi> in the New Teſtament: and ſo long as there is a <hi>Third thing</hi> wherein they agree, there is at leaſt a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of union. Even after the ſame manner hath God provided for the working and <hi>perpetuating</hi> the unity of affections by this grace of charity; in as much as there cannot be any ſort of people of ſuch an <hi>alienated eſtate from us,</hi> but there is ſome <hi>Relation</hi> in which they agree with us, and ſo long as any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>continues,</hi> even ſo long our love muſt <hi>endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay 'tis true, ſuch or ſuch an one was once my Brother in <hi>ſincere</hi> and holy <hi>profeſſion,</hi> but now he hath broke that relation and turned <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>diſſolute:</hi> yet love him ſtill, for he is thy <hi>Brother-Proteſtant:</hi> Nay, but he hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtatiz'd even to <hi>Papal ſuperſtition,</hi> and ſo hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that Relation alſo; yes, love him ſtill, for he is yet thy <hi>Brother-Chriſtian:</hi> Nay, but he is as bad as bad may be, he is degenerated into plain <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and ſo hath violated all Relations; yes, love him ſtill, for he is yet thy <hi>Brother-Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> nay, thy <hi>Brother-Man,</hi> and hath more of the lineaments and image of God in him then all the unreaſonable creatures of the world beſides; and whatſoever is <hi>of God</hi> in him, even in that he is thy Brother, and in that the <hi>fit Object</hi> of thy charity.</p>
            <p>This argument is excellently purſued by the Stoick, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as every <hi>thing,</hi> ſo every <hi>perſon</hi> hath two <hi>handles,</hi> or two <hi>capacities;</hi> and if thy charity cannot lay hold on the one, yet may it eaſily on the other: as for inſtance, ſaith he, Thy <hi>Brother hath injured thee;</hi> in this caſe do not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:171239:22"/> take him in that relation as he hath <hi>wronged thee,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for thus (as we ſay in our Engliſh phraſe) thou takeſt <hi>the Pitcher by the wrong ear,</hi> &amp; thy Brother in that capacity in which thou canſt <hi>not bear him,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but rather under this relation as he is thy <hi>Brother,</hi> born of the <hi>ſame</hi> Mother, nurſed with the <hi>ſame</hi> Milk, diſciplined in the <hi>ſame</hi> family, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. and ſo ſhalt thou receive him in that capacity in which thy <hi>charity</hi> will <hi>well bear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Thirdly true charity is durable, becauſe it hath the <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faculty</hi> to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>perſon</hi> and the <hi>fact:</hi> ſo that all diſobligements that are committed againſt love, are received, not as the effects of the <hi>perſon,</hi> but of his evil diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and proceeding not from his <hi>nature,</hi> but from the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> of his nature: By which meanes all the provocations offered againſt the endeerments of charity, are received as <hi>extrinſick</hi> to that <hi>relation</hi> in which we love our Brother, and therefore can do no prejudice, nor offer any violence to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity or conſtancy of this affection.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc. Anton.</hi> 18. Sect. 11.</note>Which was a conſideration that ſerved to pacifie the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a <hi>Heathen Emperour</hi> under the ungrateful and perverſe uſages of evil Men, when he conſidered that they had ſuch depraved apprehenſions of good and evil, of pleaſures and grief, of honour and ignominy, of life and death, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I ſhall not wonder</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nor think it a strange thing, if ſuch a man commits ſuch evil actions,</hi> to wit, of injuſtice or violence, of intemperance or riot, of indulgence or <hi>puſillanimity,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Its <hi>a ſhame for a man to be affected with wonder and amazement to ſee a Fig-tree bring forth figs:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>'tis no leſſe ſhame for a Phyſician or a Pilot to be amazed, when the one meets with Feavours, and the other with ſtormes.</hi> And even thus if we do but conſider that the diſobligements of charity are no other then the neceſſary effects of Mens evil diſpoſitions, and that ſuch <hi>corrupt affections</hi> do as naturally bring forth ſuch <hi>fruit,</hi> as the <hi>Fig-tree</hi> doth <hi>Figs,</hi> we ſhall finde little cauſe to be angry with our Brother: But like good
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:171239:22"/> 
               <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> we ſhall reſpect and love the perſon whileſt we ſeek to cure his <hi>diſeaſe:</hi> and like good <hi>Pilots</hi> in a Tempeſt, we ſhall not fret at the cauſe, but ſhall conſider how to bear up our ſelves with meekneſſe, wiſdom, and ſecurity under it: and by this meanes our charity towards our Brethren will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>durable.</hi> Which is much according to our Saviours doctrine, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.4. who teacheth us, that though our Brothers behaviour be never ſo unworthy towards us, yet we muſt continue to love and forgive, even as <hi>often as he offends.</hi> But if we once begin to ſtint our affection, and come to S. <hi>Peters ſeven times, Matth.</hi> 18.21. it is an evident ſigne that our love is but <hi>moral,</hi> or rather <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>mercenary;</hi> and not that <hi>noble, free,</hi> and <hi>generous grace</hi> of Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Text, for that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>protended</hi> and <hi>a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have we finiſhed the <hi>Third</hi> part of our Text, the <hi>Qualification</hi> of the duty, ſhewing you out of this one word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> both the <hi>extenſion, intenſion</hi> and <hi>protenſion</hi> of Chriſtian Charity.</p>
            <p>The Fourth and Laſt particular, is the <hi>Reciprocation</hi> of the duty <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Among your ſelves: The Love of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren is no ſingle ſolitary act, but it conſists in returnes and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al commerces: Let us love one another.</hi> 1 John 4.7. <hi>Bee kindly affectioned one to another,</hi> Rom. 12.10. <hi>This is the meſſage that we heard from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another:</hi> 1 John 3.11. and ſo again v. 23. and indeed, where is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocation required where ever the holy Ghoſt treats upon this ſubject of Love? The Apoſtle calls it <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. The <hi>Bond of perfection,</hi> even ſuch a bond that knits the whole world to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the world to God; with whom wee cannot ſay wherein a reciprocation is allowable, but only in Love; If hee <hi>chaſtiſeth</hi> us, we are <hi>humbled,</hi> and <hi>reformed;</hi> if he loads us with his <hi>bleſſings,</hi> we <hi>prayſe</hi> and <hi>give thanks;</hi> if hee <hi>Threatens,</hi> wee <hi>tremble;</hi> if he commands, we <hi>obey,;</hi> But if he <hi>loves</hi> us, he deſires nothing more, then that we ſhould love him again. And as is our love to God, even ſuch ſhould bee our love to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ever anſwered and cheriſhed with gratefull reciprocal returnes: God hath not placed us in Societies, like <hi>ſtones in a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:171239:23"/> heap,</hi> where there is nothing but reſervedneſs and confuſion; but like coals upon a well-built Fire, not that we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a churliſh, ſtupid and reſerved moroſity, to our brethren, and be no more communicative then ſenſeleſs ſtones; but the <hi>fervency</hi> of our Charity ſhould help to <hi>enkindle</hi> the ſame affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in our brethren, and ſo conſpire into one <hi>glorious flame</hi> of divine love. Never ſay, that ſome men are not combuſtible by this holy fire, through the <hi>churliſhneſs</hi> of their diſpoſitions, and the uncompliance of their natures, whom no kindneſs can win, nor courteſies oblige; but follow <hi>Seneca's</hi> counſell, and try the event, <hi>cinge ingratum Beneficiis, ut quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſe vertit memoriam tui fugiens, ibi te videat: beſiege ſuch a one round with favours and inſtances of Love,</hi> if <hi>one</hi> courteſy wil not gain him, try a <hi>Second,</hi> and a <hi>Third</hi> and <hi>fourth,</hi> till thou haſt ſo <hi>beſet him with the teſtimonies of thy love, that hee ſhall bee able to turn himſelf no wayes from thee, but even there hee ſhall find thee. Et vincit malos pertinax bonitas,</hi> and thou ſhalt find that a <hi>reſolute obſtinate</hi> goodneſs, wil at laſt overcome the moſt perverſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition: Methinks the holy Apoſtle gives us the very ſame encouragement under the ſame alluſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.20. <hi>If thy enemy hunger, feed him, if he thirst, give him drink, for in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thou ſhalt heap coals of fire upon his head</hi> (that is) in the ſence of ſome Expoſitors, by multiplying acts of kindneſs upon thy adverſary, thou ſhalt at the laſt enkindle in him the ſame kind affection towards thee, as thou haſt towards him, and ſo mutually conſpire in this holy <hi>flame</hi> of love.</p>
            <p>But ſtay a while, methinks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpeaks more then a bare <hi>reciprocation;</hi> and rather exhorts us to an <hi>Especial</hi> and <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate</hi> reciprocation; Before, to wit, in the 3. verſe, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpake of their converſation, in <hi>times paſt among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> when <hi>they walked in laſciviouſneſs, lusts, exceſs of Wine, &amp;c.</hi> but here hee ſpeaks of them, as received in to the faith of Chriſt, and admitted into the Church of God, and now bee ſure you have Charity <hi>among your ſelves; Sons</hi> of the <hi>ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, members</hi> of the <hi>ſame Church, sprinkled</hi> with the <hi>ſame Baptiſme, nurs'd</hi> by the <hi>ſame M nistery, ſucking</hi> the milke of the <hi>ſame Word, ſanctified</hi> by the <hi>ſame Spirit, ſaved</hi> by the <hi>ſame IESUS;</hi> Bee ſure have Charity <hi>among your ſelves:</hi> With the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:171239:23"/> world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. It comes in with an <hi>If it bee poſsible, and as much as in you lies:</hi> but as to the holy Church of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>If's</hi> at all, bee ſure, and <hi>Above all things have Charity among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods <hi>Church and People</hi> next and immediately under God himſelf, are the higheſt and moſt precious <hi>interest</hi> in the world; And as for the preſervation and good of the <hi>common beeing</hi> of nature, the God of nature hath ordered, that every <hi>ſingle b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſhall upon occaſion forſake its own proper <hi>inclination</hi> for the benefit of the <hi>natural Univerſe:</hi> ſo in a higher degree, to ſhew the prerogative of the <hi>ſacred body</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> in the region of <hi>Religion,</hi> God hath made even the <hi>Lawes of common Nature,</hi> to bee ſuperſeded for their <hi>behoof</hi> and ſervice; Thus did hee when hee made the <hi>Rock flow,</hi> the <hi>Sun return,</hi> The <hi>Sea divide,</hi> the <hi>fire not to burn,</hi> the <hi>Lions not to devour,</hi> the <hi>Viper not to sting,</hi> and many inſtances of the like nature to ſhew us, how even by the inſtitution and ſecret inſtinct from God, the mere ſenſitive and inanimate Creatures, do with all readineſs forſake their <hi>own natures</hi> and inclinations, to love and ſerve the more ſacred Intereſt of <hi>Gods Church and People:</hi> And ſhall the <hi>Rock</hi> give water to <hi>Iſrael?</hi> and ſhall wee, more <hi>obdurate</hi> then <hi>Rocks,</hi> deny a <hi>cup of cold water</hi> to one of <hi>Christs Diſciples?</hi> Shall <hi>the raging Seas</hi> bee a wall and Bulwark of protection to <hi>Gods People?</hi> and ſhall <hi>Torrentes Belial,</hi> the flood of <hi>wicked men</hi> betray &amp; <hi>overwhelm them?</hi> Shal the ſavage <hi>Lions</hi> be a guard to Gods <hi>Daniels?</hi> and ſhal more <hi>cruel man</hi> devour them? what a <hi>strange, wild, ſavage</hi> Creature is this <hi>Beast</hi> call'd <hi>man?</hi> that is leſs concern'd in the good and welfare of Gods Church and People, then either <hi>Rocks,</hi> or <hi>Seas,</hi> or <hi>Lions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I find St. <hi>Paul, Philem.</hi> 12. call <hi>Oneſimus (Pbilemons ſervant)</hi> his own <hi>Bowels,</hi> and even ſuch is every Chriſtian to his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Brother in the womb of <hi>Gods Church,</hi> and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable diviſions among ſuch brethren, are no better then ſpiritual <hi>convulſions</hi> in our <hi>own Bowels,</hi> which many times prove as <hi>mortall,</hi> as <hi>painful Diſeaſes,</hi> even to the <hi>ruine</hi> of that Church that endures them: I am not come hither to bee <hi>an unwelcom Prophet</hi> in a day of <hi>gladneſs;</hi> I ſhall only tell you what I find in the Goſpel, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.12. where one <hi>great ſigne</hi> of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:171239:24"/> of the Temple, is the <hi>coldneſs</hi> of Charity, <hi>The love of many ſhall wax cold;</hi> and truly, I know not a more ſad fatall preſage of the <hi>danger</hi> of Religion, and <hi>downfall of a Church,</hi> then the unnatulal fomenting of <hi>Schiſmes, Factions,</hi> and <hi>animoſities between Brethren</hi> of the <hi>ſame faith</hi> and <hi>profeſſion;</hi> when <hi>theſe things come to paſs,</hi> then <hi>down goes the Temple,</hi> The <hi>ſincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of Godlineſs <hi>troden under-foot,</hi> and Religion made no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe of, but to <hi>engage Parties,</hi> and give <hi>names to factions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude all, if wee bear <hi>good will</hi> to <hi>Sion,</hi> if wee tender the honor <hi>of God,</hi> or welfare of <hi>Religion,</hi> or the Peace and quiet of <hi>our own ſouls,</hi> let us purſue with all holy and devout Zeal, after this grace of Chriſtian Charity <hi>(if it bee poſſible)</hi> with <hi>all men;</hi> but above all things, <hi>amongst our ſelves.</hi> And then what ever our corporal proviſions ſhall this day bee, it is this <hi>holy Love</hi> that will bee our <hi>good Cheer.</hi> Whereby our <hi>Feaſt</hi> wil deſerve the ſame Encomium which <hi>Hugo de San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto Victore</hi> gives of the Feaſt of a good Conſcience; It wil bee <hi>Titulus Religionis, Templum Solomonis, Ager Benedictionis, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus deliciarum, gaudium Angelorum, Arca foederis, Aula Dei, &amp; Habitaculum Spiritus Sancti.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hugo</hi> Victor. de Anima. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>It will bee as the Title and proſpect of Religion, the Temple of Solomon, the Field of Bleſsing, the Garden of Delights, the joy of Angels, the Ark of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the Court of God, and the habitation of the holy Spirit;</hi> unto whom with the Father and the Son bee aſcribed all honor, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Praiſe, Obedience and adoration, now, and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>P. 2. l. 18. for <hi>fifth</hi> r. <hi>firſt.</hi> Ib. l. 22. for <hi>of</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi> p. 11. l. 12. for <hi>precedent</hi> r. <hi>precedence.</hi> p. 14. l. 32. for <hi>when</hi> r. <hi>where.</hi> p. 15. l. ult. for <hi>charge</hi> r. <hi>change.</hi> p. 32. l. 2. for <hi>but</hi> r. <hi>yet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171239:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
